A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Associate Director, Office Files of Robert M. Hutchins FA703
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Associate Director, Office Files of Robert M. Hutchins
1950-1956
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA703
5.28 Cubic Feet
Conditions Governing Access
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research.
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Biographical / Historical
Robert M. Hutchins (1899-1977) was an educator, academic administrator and foundation leader who served as Associate Director of the Ford Foundation from 1951-1954. Hutchins was hired by the Foundation’s new President, Paul G. Hoffman, to provide input on the development of grant portfolios related to education, civil liberties, civil rights and international cooperation. He played a key role in the establishment and early activities of three independent funds created by the Foundation: the Fund for Adult Education, the Fund for the Advancement of Education and the Fund for the Republic. Because Hoffman spent a great deal of time traveling during his tenure as President, Hutchins played a strong role in the overall administration of Foundation affairs and in managing the Pasadena headquarters. Hutchins left the Ford Foundation in 1954 to become President of the Fund for the Republic.
Prior to joining the Foundation, Hutchins came to prominence as President (1929-1945) and Chancellor (1945-1951) of the University of Chicago. He was a widely known, and frequently controversial, authority in the field of higher education. Hutchins was Chairman of the Board of Editors of Encyclopedia Britannica from 1943-1974.
Scope and Contents
The Office Files of Robert M. Hutchins document the early development and implementation of Ford Foundation grant portfolios related to education, civil liberties, public television and refugee assistance during the years 1950-1956. The records provide insight into how Foundation staff and trustees acted on the programmatic recommendations of the Gaither Study Committee's Report of the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program (1949). They also offer a rare glimpse of the daily operation and administration of Foundation affairs under the leadership of President Paul G. Hoffman, when the institution was headquartered in Pasadena, California. The files contain correspondence with grant seekers, staff and trustees, reports by consultants and grantees, conference materials, staff memoranda, program planning information, meeting minutes, publications and clippings. The collection measures 4 linear feet and is contained in 12 archival boxes.
Arrangement
The Office Files of Robert M. Hutchins are arranged in two series:
I. Correspondence, 1950-1956 II. Subjects, 1950-1954
Ford Foundation
- Correspondence, 1950-1956; I
  Scope and Contents
  Filed here are incoming and outgoing letters, telegrams, memoranda and attachments that document the inception and early operation of Ford Foundation grant programs with an emphasis on fields overseen by Hutchins, which included education, civil liberties and cultural affairs. There is also substantial information concerning Foundation activities related to the promotion of international cooperation and refugee assistance.
  Highlights include numerous letters and memos exchanged with staff that illuminate decision making processes and lines of authority as the five program areas delineated in the Gaither report were first implemented. Staff memos also contain valuable information regarding the administrative structure of the Foundation, the relationship between the Pasadena and New York offices, early public relations efforts, and internal reaction to investigations of the Foundation by the U.S. Congress's Cox Committee and Reece Committee.
  Numerous letters from the philosopher Mortimer J. Adler document his influence on Hutchins's program in the field of education. Correspondence with editor and publisher James Laughlin shows that Hutchins and Foundation advisor W. H. "Ping" Ferry were each closely involved with Laughlin's work as head of the Foundation-supported Intercultural Publications and the journal Perspectives. Conditions facing European war refugees are discussed extensively in files on the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees. Finally, there are a small number of items that date from after Hutchins's departure from the Foundation, and which document the first months of his tenure as President of the Fund for the Republic.
  Arrangement
  These files are arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Abrams, Frank W., 1952 (Box 1 (SK 46627), Folder 1)
  - Adler, Mortimer J., 1951-1955 (Box 1 (SK 46627), Folder 2-6)
  - Agar, Herbert, 1953 (Box 1 (SK 46627), Folder 7)
  - American Friends Service Committee, 1951-1954 (Box 2 (SK 46628), Folder 1-2)
  - Anshen, Ruth Nanda, 1952 (Box 2 (SK 46628), Folder 3)
  - Ariss, R. M., 1952 (Box 2 (SK 46628), Folder 4)
  - Asia Institute, 1951 (Box 2 (SK 46628), Folder 5)
  - B, miscellaneous, 1951-1953 (Box 2 (SK 46628), Folder 6)
  - Berelson, Bernard, 1950-1955 (Box 2 (SK 46628), Folder 7-8)
  - Bissell, Richard M., Jr., 1952 (Box 2 (SK 46628), Folder 9)
  - British Broadcasting Corporation (BBC), 1951-1953 (Box 2 (SK 46628), Folder 10)
  - Brown, Dyke, 1951-1953 (Box 2 (SK 46628), Folder 11)
  - Brown, Harrison, 1951 (Box 2 (SK 46628), Folder 12)
  - C, miscellaneous, 1951-1953 (Box 3 (SK 46629), Folder 1)
  - China Institute of America, 1951-1952 (Box 3 (SK 46629), Folder 2)
  - Clark, Colin, 1951-1954 (Box 3 (SK 46629), Folder 3)
  - Clark, Greenville, 1951-1955 (Box 3 (SK 46629), Folder 4-6)
  - D, miscellaneous, 1951-1954 (Box 3 (SK 46629), Folder 7)
  - Dahlberg, Edward, 1953 (Box 3 (SK 46629), Folder 8)
  - David, Donald K., 1952 (Box 3 (SK 46629), Folder 9)
  - Davis, Chester C., 1952 (Box 3 (SK 46629), Folder 10)
  - Diogenes, 1951-1953 (Box 3 (SK 46629), Folder 11)
  - E, miscellaneous, 1953-1955 (Box 3 (SK 46629), Folder 12)
  - Eliot, Charles, 1952 (Box 3 (SK 46629), Folder 13)
  - F, miscellaneous, 1951-1955 (Box 3 (SK 46629), Folder 14)
  - Ferry, W. H. (Ping), 1951-1954 (Box 3 (SK 46629), Folder 15)
  - Fletcher, C. Scott, 1951 (Box 3 (SK 46629), Folder 16)
  - Ford, Henry II, 1951-1953 (Box 3 (SK 46629), Folder 17)
  - Fox, Melvin J., 1951-1953 (Box 3 (SK 46629), Folder 18)
  - Fund for the Republic, 1952-1956 (Box 4 (SK46630), Folder 1)
  - G, miscellaneous, 1953-1955 (Box 4 (SK46630), Folder 2)
  - Gaither, Rowan H., 1951-1953 (Box 4 (SK46630), Folder 3)
  - Gladieux, Bernard L., 1951-1954 (Box 4 (SK46630), Folder 4)
  - Goldschmidt, Walter, 1953 (Box 4 (SK46630), Folder 5)
  - H, miscellaneous, 1952-1955 (Box 4 (SK46630), Folder 6)
  - Hoffman, Paul G., 1950-1954 (Box 4 (SK46630), Folder 7)
  - Howard, John B., 1951-1954 (Box 4 (SK46630), Folder 8)
  - Hutchins, Robert M. – rejection letters to grant seekers, 1954 (Box 4 (SK46630), Folder 9)
  - Huxley, Aldous, 1952 (Box 4 (SK46630), Folder 10)
  - Huxley, Julian, 1951 (Box 4 (SK46630), Folder 11)
  - I, miscellaneous, 1951-1955 (Box 5 (SK 46631), Folder 1)
  - Institute of International Education, 1951-1952 (Box 5 (SK 46631), Folder 2)
  - International Press Institute, 1951-1954 (Box 5 (SK 46631), Folder 3)
  - J, miscellaneous, 1954 (Box 5 (SK 46631), Folder 4)
  - K, miscellaneous, 1951-1955 (Box 5 (SK 46631), Folder 5)
  - Kabir, Humayun, 1951 (Box 5 (SK 46631), Folder 6)
  - Katz, Milton (Box 5 (SK 46631), Folder 7)
  - Kennan, George F., 1951-1952 (Box 5 (SK 46631), Folder 8)
  - L, miscellaneous, 1951-1954 (Box 5 (SK 46631), Folder 9)
  - Laughlin, James, 1951-1953 (Box 5 (SK 46631), Folder 10-12)
  - Lazersfeld, Paul, 1952-1953 (Box 5 (SK 46631), Folder 13)
  - Lippman, Walter, 1951 (Box 5 (SK 46631), Folder 14)
  - Luce, Clare Booth, 1951 (Box 5 (SK 46631), Folder 15)
  - M, miscellaneous, 1951-1954 (Box 5 (SK 46631), Folder 16)
  - McDaniel, Joseph, 1951-1954 (Box 6 (SK 46632), Folder 1-2)
  - May, Oliver, 1951-1954 (Box 6 (SK 46632), Folder 3)
  - Moore, M. T., 1952 (Box 6 (SK 46632), Folder 4)
  - N, miscellaneous, 1951-1954 (Box 6 (SK 46632), Folder 5)
  - National Association of Educational Broadcasters, 1953 (Box 6 (SK 46632), Folder 6)
  - Newsom, Earl, 1951-1952 (Box 6 (SK 46632), Folder 7)
  - Nielsen, Waldemar, 1953-1954 (Box 6 (SK 46632), Folder 8)
  - O, miscellaneous, 1951-1954 (Box 6 (SK 46632), Folder 9)
  - Olivetti, Adriano, 1952-1954 (Box 6 (SK 46632), Folder 10)
  - P, miscellaneous, 1951-1954 (Box 6 (SK 46632), Folder 11)
  - Pascal, Gabriel, 1953 (Box 6 (SK 46632), Folder 12)
  - Patchen, Kenneth, 1952-1954 (Box 6 (SK 46632), Folder 13)
  - Price, Don K., 1954 (Box 6 (SK 46632), Folder 14)
  - Public Affairs Institute, 1951 (Box 6 (SK 46632), Folder 15)
  - Puma, Fernando, 1954 (Box 6 (SK 46632), Folder 16)
  - Quigley, Martin, 1951-1953 (Box 6 (SK 46632), Folder 17)
  - Quinn, J. A., 1952-1954 (Box 6 (SK 46632), Folder 18)
  - R, miscellaneous, 1951-1954 (Box 7 (SK46633), Folder 1)
  - Redfield, Robert, 1951-1953 (Box 7 (SK46633), Folder 2)
  - Regarding Look magazine article by Hutchins, 1954 (Box 7 (SK46633), Folder 3)
  - Roper, Elmo, 1952-1953 (Box 7 (SK46633), Folder 4)
  - S, miscellaneous, 1951-1954 (Box 7 (SK46633), Folder 5)
  - Salomon, Irving, 1952-1955 (Box 7 (SK46633), Folder 6)
  - Schwartz, Delmore, 1953 (Box 7 (SK46633), Folder 7)
  - Schweitzer, Albert, 1951-1953 (Box 7 (SK46633), Folder 8)
  - Sereno, Renzo, 1951-1953 (Box 8 (SK 46634), Folder 1)
  - Shuster, George, 1952 (Box 8 (SK 46634), Folder 2)
  - South African Institute of Race Relations, 1953 (Box 8 (SK 46634), Folder 3)
  - Spaeth, Carl B., 1952-1953 (Box 8 (SK 46634), Folder 4)
  - Sternberg, Fritz, 1953-1954 (Box 8 (SK 46634), Folder 5)
  - T, miscellaneous, 1952-1954 (Box 8 (SK 46634), Folder 6)
  - U, miscellaneous, 1953 (Box 8 (SK 46634), Folder 7)
  - Union of International Associations Service Centre for Non-Governmental Organizations, 1951 (Box 8 (SK 46634), Folder 8)
  - United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees, 1952-1954 (Box 8 (SK 46634), Folder 9-11)
  - V, miscellaneous, 1953-1955 (Box 8 (SK 46634), Folder 12)
  - W, miscellaneous, 1951-1955 (Box 9 (SK 46635), Folder 1)
  - Ward, F. Champion, 1952-1953 (Box 9 (SK 46635), Folder 2)
  - Werner, M. R., n.d. (Box 9 (SK 46635), Folder 3)
  - Wyzanski, Charles, 1952-1954 (Box 9 (SK 46635), Folder 4)
  - Y-Z, miscellaneous, 1951-1954 (Box 9 (SK 46635), Folder 5)
  - Young, E. L., 1953-1954 (Box 9 (SK 46635), Folder 6)
  - Young, James Webb, 1951-1954 (Box 9 (SK 46635), Folder 7)
- Subjects, 1950-1954; II
  This series contains reports, publications, clippings, conference and seminar materials, memoranda, meeting minutes and other records concerning Foundation grantees, programs and administration. There are substantial files documenting the inception of Foundation portfolios in the fields of public television, overseas training and research, academic exchanges and public affairs. Also filed here are records pertaining to the Fund for Adult Education and the Fund for the Advancement of Education. Additional records document the creation of policies and procedures for the day to day administration of Foundation affairs.
  These files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - American Association for the United Nations, 1951 (Box 9 (SK 46635), Folder 8)
  - American Films Abroad, 1952 (Box 9 (SK 46635), Folder 9)
  - American Heritage Council, 1951 (Box 9 (SK 46635), Folder 10)
  - Behaviorism, 1954, n.d. (Box 9 (SK 46635), Folder 11)
  - Board on Overseas Training and Research, 1952-1953 (Box 9 (SK 46635), Folder 12)
  - Commission on Television, 1952-1953 (Box 9 (SK 46635), Folder 13)
  - Cox Committee, 1952-1953 (Box 10 (SK 46636), Folder 1)
  - East European Fund, 1952 (Box 10 (SK 46636), Folder 2)
  - Exchange of persons, 1951-1952 (Box 10 (SK 46636), Folder 3)
  - Foundation policies, 1951-1952 (Box 10 (SK 46636), Folder 4)
  - Foundation publishing house (Box 10 (SK 46636), Folder 5)
  - Free Russia Fund, 1951 (Box 10 (SK 46636), Folder 6)
  - Free University of Berlin, 1951-1953 (Box 10 (SK 46636), Folder 7)
  - Fund for Adult Education, 1951-1954 (Box 10 (SK 46636), Folder 8)
  - Fund for the Advancement of Education, 1951-1954 (Box 10 (SK 46636), Folder 9)
  - George Peabody College, 1951 (Box 10 (SK 46636), Folder 10)
  - Grant approval, 1952 (Box 10 (SK 46636), Folder 11)
  - New Asia College, 1953 (Box 10 (SK 46636), Folder 12)
  - On the Record, 1953-1954 (Box 10 (SK 46636), Folder 13)
  - Overseas program, 1951-1953 (Box 10 (SK 46636), Folder 14)
  - Program Area I, 1951-1953 (Box 10 (SK 46636), Folder 15)
  - Program Planning Division staff meetings, 1951 (Box 10 (SK 46636), Folder 16)
  - Public Administration Clearing House, 1951-1952 (Box 11 (SK 46637), Folder 1)
  - Resources for the Future, 1952-1953 (Box 11 (SK 46637), Folder 2)
  - Resources program, 1952-1953 (Box 11 (SK 46637), Folder 3)
  - Seminar on Education, 1952 (Box 11 (SK 46637), Folder 4)
  - Seminar on Freedom, 1951 (Box 11 (SK 46637), Folder 5)
  - Seminar on Peace, 1951 (Box 11 (SK 46637), Folder 6)
  - Staff meeting minutes, 1951-1952 (Box 11 (SK 46637), Folder 7-8)
  - Staff meeting minutes, 1953 (Box 12 (SK 46638), Folder 1)
  - Television, 1952-1954 (Box 12 (SK 46638), Folder 2)
  - Television-Radio Workshop, 1951-1954 (Box 12 (SK 46638), Folder 3-4)
  - United Nations, 1952-1953 (Box 12 (SK 46638), Folder 5)
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization, 1950-1953 (Box 12 (SK 46638), Folder 6)
  - University of Chicago, 1950-1952 (Box 12 (SK 46638), Folder 7)
  - Washington Seminar, 1952 (Box 12 (SK 46638), Folder 8)